I see. So Raetsel's headed for that place?
（エニグマ）そうか
レイツェルは　例の場所に向かったか。
分かった。　監視を続けろ。
Very well. Keep an eye on them.
時間が　かかってしまった。
It's taken quite a while,
でも　もうすぐ完成するよ
ラヴーシュカ。→
but it's about to be completed, Lovushka.
The puzzle of our revenge.
僕たち２人の　復讐のパズルが…　フフフ。
（大門カイト）話って何だ？　学園長。
What did you want to talk about, Principal?
Yeah, you called us here in such a hurry.
（逆之上ギャモン）ああ。　急に　俺たちを
こんな所に呼び出しやがって。
（井藤ノノハ）何か　レイツェルとジンさんの
手がかりが→
Did you find some clues about Raetsel and Jin?
見つかったんですか？
There used to be a POG training facility on this island.
（解道バロン）この島には　かつて
ＰＯＧの訓練施設がありました。
えっ？
学園長やジンも→
So you and Jin practiced puzzling here?
この島で
パズルの修業を積んでたってのか？
（バロン）はい。
Yes.
（アナ・グラム）そのお墓　ひょっとして
バロバロとジンジンのお友達の…。
Is that a grave of your and Jinjin's friend?
She was Jin's rival.
彼女は　ジンのライバルでした。
ジンの!?
Jin's?
パズルを愛し　パズルに殉じた
一人のソルヴァー→
She was a Solver who sacrificed herself for the puzzles she loved.
ラヴーシュカ。
Lovushka.
（フリーセル）古代文字の解読は　パズルと
よく似てるって聞いた事がある。
I heard that decoding ancient scripts is similar to solving a puzzle.
法則さえ　つかめれば…。
You just need to figure out the rules governing it.
カイトの事かい？
Thinking about Kaito?
（ルーク・盤城・クロスフィールド）まだ
何も終わっていなかったんだ。→
Nothing was over.
神の書　神のパズル。
（フリーセル）それに　オルペウスの腕輪。→
The Divine Scripture, the Puzzle of God...
And the Orpheus Rings too.
学園長は　あの話を　カイトに…。
（ルーク）するだろうね。
Will the Principal tell Kaito?
Probably.
また一つ　神のパズルによって
生み出された　悲しい物語を…。
This is just another tragedy of the Puzzle of God.
ラヴーシュカ？
Lovushka?
We graduated Root Academy and joined the POG.
√学園を卒業した私とジンは
ＰＯＧに入りました。→
We met her there,
そこで　彼女と出会ったのです。
回想
（真方ジン）ん？
（バロン）どうした？　ジン。
What's wrong, Jin?
（ラヴーシュカ）
ごちそうさまでした。　感謝！→
That was good. Thanks.
My stomach's full, so back to the fun.
さて　腹ごしらえも終わったし…。
よし！
Good!
５秒６８!?
へえ～。
5.68 seconds?
ん？
（バロン）そうか　君が　ラヴーシュカだね。
Oh, so you're Lovushka?
And who're you? Why do you know about me?
えっと…　誰だっけ？
何で　あたしの事　知ってんの？
他に　もう一人　ソルヴァーが入ったとは
聞いていたけど…。
I heard there was one more Solver.
You're not half bad.
さすがに　やるな。
ああ。→
お前と同じタイムだな。
同じタイム？
She did it in the same time as you.
The same time?
あっ！　じゃあ　ひょっとして
あんたが真方ジン？→
Then you're Makata Jin and Kaidou Baron?
で　あんたが　解道バロン？
え？
（ジン）
何で　俺たちの事　知ってんだ？
How do you know about us?
I heard there was an awesome Solver and Giver pair joining.
（ラヴーシュカ）
すごいソルヴァーと　相棒のギヴァーが
入ったって聞いたからね。→
あたし　ラヴーシュカ。　よろしく！
I'm Lovushka. Nice to meet you.
ああ…　よろしく。
Yeah, likewise.
よろしくね。
You too.
フフッ　よろしく！
Yeah.
（バロン）彼女も　ジン同様
ＰＯＧでは異例のソルヴァーでした。
She, just like Jin, was an exceptional Solver in the POG.
ってこたぁ　その女も…。
（軸川ソウジ）ああ。
So that girl was like him?
Yeah, a Phi Brain candidate picked out by Count Pythagoras.
ピタゴラス伯爵によって見いだされた
ファイ・ブレイン候補の一人。
（バロン）当時の私たちは　まだ→
At that point we knew nothing about the Count's plot.
伯爵の陰謀に
気付いていませんでしたがね…。
Jin was just a bit better than her at puzzles.
（バロン）パズル能力は　ジンの方が
一歩　勝っていました。→
ジンは　ラヴーシュカに追われる事で
ラヴーシュカは　ジンを追う事で→
For Jin, the challenge of Lovushka,
and for Lovushka, challenging Jin
was how they helped each other improve.
互いに高め合い
よきライバルとなっていったのです。
They became good rivals.
回想
よく食うなあ。
You eat those all the time.
（ラヴーシュカ）
ここに来て　初めて食べたけどさ
お米って　おいしいね。→
I had rice for the first time when I came here. It's really good, you know.
塩むすび…　塩！　米！　シンプル！
（ジン）分かった　分かった。
A salted rice ball. Just salt and rice.
It's so simple!
I get it.
あたしの国はさ　貧しくって→
You know, my country's so poor
こんなおいしいもの
食べられなかったんだ。
that I could never eat something this good there.
おもちゃも　手作りの
パズルくらいしかなかったし。
The only toys I had were handmade puzzles too.
そっか…。
I see.
あたしさ　夢があるんだ。
夢？
I have a dream, you know.
A dream?
伯爵のお手伝いをして
神のパズルを解いて→
I want to help the Count, solve the Puzzle of God,
神の書を　手に入れて…。→
get the Divine Scripture,
おなかいっぱいの世界を
つくりたいの。
and make a world where no one's hungry.
（ジン）おなかいっぱいの世界？
（ラヴーシュカ）そう！→
A world where no one's hungry, huh?
Yeah. A world where everyone can eat delicious food until they're full.
みんなが　おなかいっぱい
おいしいものを食べられる…→
そんな世界。
へえ～。　いい夢だな。
That's a nice dream.
ヘヘッ。　あたしも
世界中のおいしいもの→
I wanna try all the yummy food around the world too.
全部　食べたいしね。
ジンは？　ジンの夢って何？
And what about you? What's your dream, Jin?
（ジン）俺？　俺は決まってる。→
Me? You even need to ask?
ファイ・ブレインになって
神のパズルを解く事だ。
I wanna become the Phi Brain and solve the Puzzle of God.
Then what?
（ラヴーシュカ）で　どうするの？
（ジン）どうするって　何を？
What do you mean?
（ラヴーシュカ）神の書を　手に入れて→
Isn't there something you want to achieve by getting the Divine Scripture?
何か　かなえたい事が
あるんじゃないの？
Not really.
別に。　神のパズルってのは
世界で一番難しいパズルなんだろ？
The Puzzle of God is the most difficult puzzle out there, right?
I can't stay put until I've solved it!
だったら　解くっきゃないってね。
パズルバカ…。
（ジン）
お前に言われたくねえって！
Puzzle maniac.
Rich coming from you!
ふ～ん　「解くっきゃない」か。
ジンらしいね。
You can't stay put, huh? That's just like you.
That was good. Thanks.
（ラヴーシュカ）ごちそうさま。
感謝。
でも　ジンの夢は　かなわない。
But your dream won't be fulfilled. I'll become the Phi Brain.
ファイ・ブレインになるのは
あたしだからね。
ヘッ！　言ってくれるぜ。
Big words.
However, as time passed,
（バロン）ですが…　時がたち→
the gap between her and Jin widened.
ジンと彼女の力の差は
どんどん広がっていきました。→
めきめきと
腕を上げていくジンに→
Jin kept improving at a blinding speed,
and Lovushka couldn't keep up with him anymore.
ラヴーシュカは追いつけなくなって
いったのです。→
Then...
そして…。
Jin, is that the Orpheus Armlet?
回想
（ラヴーシュカ）ジン。
それが　オルペウスの腕輪？
ほんとに　手に入れたんだ！
You really got it!
Yeah. Now I'm one step closer to becoming the Phi Brain.
ああ。　これで　また一歩
ファイ・ブレインに近づいたぜ。
まだまだ
あたしだって負けないからね！
I haven't give up either!
Good.
（バロン）しかし　ジンは→
But Jin saw a future where Count Pythagoras destroys the world.
ピタゴラス伯爵が世界を滅ぼす未来を
見てしまったのです。→
You know the rest.
あとは
君たちも知ってのとおり…。
それで　ラヴーシュカさんは？
What happened to Lovushka?
ジンが失踪したと聞いた彼女は
とてもショックを受けていたそうです。
It was a huge shock for her when she heard that Jin ran off.
回想
うそ…　ジンが!?
No way! He did? That can't be!
そんな…。
（バロン）その後　彼女は
愚者のパズルに挑むようになり…。
After that, she started challenging Fools' Puzzles.
Lovushka... died?!
回想
（バロン）死んだ…　ラヴーシュカが!?
She lost her life to a Fools' Puzzle.
愚者のパズルで
命を落としたそうです。
（キュービック・Ｇ）どうして　そこまで…。
Why would she...
ファイ・ブレインになるためにってか。
To become a Phi Brain?
おなかいっぱいの世界…。
The world where no one's hungry...
I guess she wanted to fulfill her dream that badly.
それだけ
夢をかなえたかったんだろうね。
I'm not sure.
本当に　そうなのかな？
えっ？
ラヴラヴは　いい子。
Lovlov was a good girl,
でも…　どこかで
夢が　ねじれちゃったのかも。
but her dream might've gotten twisted at some point.
夢が　ねじれた？
Her dream got twisted, you say?
で…　何で　そんな話を俺たちに？
Why are you telling us about this?
ああ。　前置きが長ぇのは
あんたの悪い癖だぜ　学園長。
Yeah. It always takes ages for you to get to the point, Principal.
前置き？　今の話が？
Wait, so this wasn't the point?
（ギャモン）本番は　これからだろ？→
The real deal comes after this.
Dunno what you've got up your sleeve, but tell us already!
さあ…　何だか知らねえが
さっさと話せよ。
ラヴーシュカさんには婚約者がいてね。
Lovushka was engaged.
Jikukawa?
（キュービック）軸川先輩!?
（ギャモン）…って　そっちかよ！
You're gonna tell us?!
He was from the same country as her, and was her childhood friend.
彼は　ラヴーシュカさんと同じ国の出身で
幼なじみ。
彼女の専属ギヴァーとして
パズルを作り続けていたそうだ。
He kept making puzzles for her as her own Giver.
（バロン）ラヴーシュカの死後　交通事故で
命を失ったと聞いていましたが…。
I was told that he died in a traffic accident soon after Lovushka.
生きていたんだ。
He's still alive.
えっ？
事故で死んだと見せかけて→
He faked his death in an accident, erased his identity,
自分の存在を抹消し
別人として生きていたんだ。
and lived on as a different person.
Why would he?
どうして　そんな事を…。
ラヴーシュカさんが死んだ　そのころ→
About the time Lovushka died, their home country's economy
彼女の祖国は　レアメタルの採掘で
急速な経済成長を始めてね。
started growing rapidly, fueled by its rare metal mining industry.
彼は　その混乱に紛れ
国の中枢に潜り込み→
He hid in that chaos, and infiltrated the country.
ついに　トップにまで上り詰めた。
He made it to the very top.
The top?
トップ？
まさか　そいつは…。
Are you telling me it's him?!
彼とラヴーシュカの祖国は　アムギーネ共和国。
He and Lovushka were from the Republic of Amgine.
エニグマ！
Enigma!
No.
いや…。
ザガートカ。
Zagadka...
そう。　私は　ザガートカ。
Indeed, I am Zagadka.
And Lovushka was the one I loved.
そして　ラヴーシュカは　我が最愛の人…。
Enigma! What are you doing here?!
エニグマ…　どうして　ここに!?
I noticed people snooping around me again. I told you I wouldn't hide anything.
また　私の周りを
嗅ぎ回っていたようなのでね。→
言ったろう？　隠し事はしないと。
お手を煩わせてしまった
ようですね。　すみません。
Pardon me for bothering you.
You noticed after all, Baron.
やはり気付いたか　バロン。
In Amgine, the government keeps a tight lid on information.
アムギーネは　情報統制の厳しい国。→
裏付け調査には　てこずりましたが
軸川君が　よくやってくれました。
It wasn't easy to look for proof, but Jikukawa did great.
決め手は　この写真です。
This photo was the key.
When I zoomed in, I found...
拡大してみると…。
何かの傷痕？
Some kind of scar?
（バロン）ザガートカも　同じ場所に
古傷を持っていた。→
Zagadka had an old scar at the same place as well.
幼い頃　落石から　ラヴーシュカを守り
出来たと聞いているが…。
I heard you got it protecting Lovushka from a falling rock when you were young.
In the starving lands of our poor homeland, we lived supporting each other.
（エニグマ）
祖国の　貧しい痩せた大地で→
２人で　肩を寄せ合い
生きてきた。
Nothing could remove this from me.
消せるはずがない。
（バロン）名前や顔は変えられても→
So you changed your name and face, but you couldn't abandon her?
彼女との絆を消す事は
できなかったというわけか…。
全部うそだったのか？
So it was all lies?
About Jin hating puzzles,
ジンが　パズルを憎んでた
っていうのも→
マスターブレインたちを集めろって
お前に頼んだのも　全部！
and that he asked you to gather Master Brains,
all of it?!
Of course.
ああ　うそさ。
（ギャモン）んだと　こらぁ！
What the fuck?!
ラヴーシュカのためか？
えっ？
Was it for Lovushka?
（バロン）パズルに命を奪われた
彼女の復讐を…。
A puzzle killed her. This is revenge.
そう。　全て　ラヴーシュカのため。
Indeed. It's all for her.
大統領になったのも
全てのパズラーを滅ぼすのも→
I became president and set out to annihilate all puzzlers just for her.
ラヴーシュカのためさ。
ラヴーシュカさんは
パズルを愛していたんでしょ？
But she loved puzzles!
Then there's no way she'd be happy with this!
じゃあ　そんな事しても
喜ぶはずがない！
黙れ！
Silence!
お前たちに　ラヴーシュカの何が分かる。
What do you even know about Lovushka?
ラヴーシュカが　どれだけ
パズルに苦しめられていたか…。
Do you have any idea how much she suffered because of puzzles?
回想
（ザガートカ）食べないのかい？
ラヴーシュカ。
You're not gonna eat, Lovushka?
ねえ　ザガートカ。
You know, Zagadka...
何だい？
What?
あたし…　あたしね
パズル　やめようかなって…。
I've been thinking that I should quit puzzling.
（ラヴーシュカ）
ジンは腕輪に選ばれたのに
あたしは選ばれない。→
Jin was chosen by the Armlet, not me.
パズルをすればするほど
ジンの背中が遠のいていく…。
The more we puzzle, the further ahead of me he gets.
違うんだよ　ジンは…
あたしにはない何かを持ってる。
Jin's different. He has something I lack.
あたしには…　あたしには
足りないんだ　何かが…。
I'm not good enough. Just not good enough!
That's not true!
そんな事ないよ！　あんな男に
君の夢が負けるはずがない！→
Your dream is stronger than that guy's!
頑張ろうよ　ラヴーシュカ。
Don't give up, Lovushka!
You have heard about Makata Jin, have you not?
（ピタゴラス伯爵）
真方ジンの事は聞いているな？
はい。
Yes.
（ピタゴラス伯爵）
やつは　神の書を手に入れ→
He wants to pursue his own ambitions by getting the Divine Scripture.
己の野望を　成就させようと
しているのだ。
But... Jin's not like that!
（ラヴーシュカ）そんな！
ジンは　そんな人じゃ…。
（ピタゴラス伯爵）
では　なぜ姿を消した？
Then why would he disappear?
I don't know.
それは…。
お前の夢も　かなわんぞ。
えっ？
Your dream will fall apart too.
If he takes the Divine Scripture first,
（ピタゴラス伯爵）あやつが先に
神の書を　手に入れれば→
お前の祖国も
愛する者たちも救えはせん。
you won't be able to save your homeland or those you love.
ファイ・ブレインとなれ。
Become the Phi Brain.
真方ジンよりも先に
ファイ・ブレインとなるのだ。
You must become the Phi Brain before Makata Jin.
やろう　ラヴーシュカ。
でも…。
Let's do it, Lovushka.
But...
ジンに　神の書を奪われたら→
If Jin takes the Divine Scripture, then your—our dream will be done for.
君の…
僕たちの夢が終わってしまう。
僕にとっては　君の夢が一番だ。
Your dream is my top priority.
どんな事をしても
かなえてみせる。
ザガートカ…。
I'll make it come true, no matter what.
Zagadka...
僕たちの夢を
２人のパズルを守ろう　ラヴーシュカ。
Let's protect our dream... our puzzles, Lovushka!
うっ…。
（ザガートカ）ラヴーシュカ！
Lovushka!
You should eat something. It's for your own good.
（ザガートカ）
少しは食べなきゃ　体に毒だよ。
弱気になっちゃ駄目だ。
Don't give up just yet.
大丈夫だよ　君なら
きっと　ファイ・ブレインになれる。→
It's fine. I'm sure you can become the Phi Brain.
頑張ろう。
Let's keep it up.
おなか…　いっぱいの…
世界…。→
A world... where no one's... hungry...
おなか…　いっぱいの…　世界…。
Good luck, Lovushka!
頑張って！　ラヴーシュカ！
（ザガートカ）ラヴーシュカ…？　ラヴーシュカ！
Lovushka! Lovushka!
うそだ…　そんな…。→
That... can't be...
ラヴーシュカ!!
Lovushka!
今なら分かる。　伯爵は
ラヴーシュカを利用していたんだ。
Now I understand that the Count simply used Lovushka.
夢が　ねじれちゃった…。
Her dream got twisted.
てめえが　今　レイツェルにしてる事も
同じじゃねえか!?
You're doing the same shit with Raetsel now!
The Count used Lovushka. You use Raetsel.
伯爵は　ラヴーシュカを利用した。
あなたは　レイツェルを…。
アムギーネは　豊かな国になったのに…。
But Amgine flourishes...
ラヴラヴは　大好きな人たちが
幸せになるのを→
Lovlov didn't get to see those she loved become happy.
見る事ができなかったんだね。
So I fulfilled her dream in her stead.
（エニグマ）だから　私が代わりに
彼女の夢をかなえたのだ。
I made Amgine as it is now. I turned it into the country she dreamed of.
（エニグマ）私が　今のアムギーネを…
彼女が望んだ国を築いた。
それは　おかしい。
That's not right.
Amgine's rare metal boom started before Lovushka died.
アムギーネが　レアメタルで発展を始めたのは
ラヴーシュカさんが亡くなる直前だ。
Yeah! That's got nothing to do with you!
じゃあ　てめえは関係ねえだろ!?
And then, Lovushka wouldn't have had to overexert herself in puzz—
それに…　だったら　ラヴーシュカさんは
無理にパズルを解かなくても…。
Wait, you didn't tell her?
まさか！　黙ってたの…？
もうじき国が豊かになると
知ってて　彼女に教えなかった。
You knew that your country was on the path to wealth,
and you didn't tell her.
まさか…　どうして　そんな事!?
No way! Why would you do that?
（エニグマ）国を救うのは　ラヴーシュカだ。→
The country must be saved by Lovushka.
他の誰かに　先を越されるなど
あってはならない事だ！
No one may do it before her!
そんな！
No way...
You killed her, didn't you?!
貴様だろうが！
彼女の命を奪ったのは。
（エニグマ）
パズルだ…　全部　パズルが悪いんだ！
The puzzles! The puzzles are to blame!
ザガートカ！
貴様が　ラヴーシュカを追い込んだ！→
Zagadka, you chased Lovushka to her death!
貴様が！　自分の手で！
学園長…。
You and no one else!
Principal...
フッ。　この世に　パズルさえなければ
ラヴーシュカは死なずに済んだ。
If there weren't any puzzles, Lovushka wouldn't have had to die.
The Count wouldn't have had anything to plot with.
伯爵が野望を抱く事も！　フフフ…。
な…　何だ　こいつ。
What's wrong with this guy?
恋人を失った悲しみを
パズルに　ぶつけてる。
He's directing all his grief from losing his love at puzzles.
He's blaming puzzles for everything.
全て　パズルのせいにしてるんだ。
とんだ逆恨み野郎だぜ。
That's quite the made-up grudge.
（エニグマ）大門カイト！
Daimon Kaito!
お前の両親が死ぬ事も→
The death of your parents,
ルークや　ファイ・ブレインの子供たちが
過酷な運命をたどる事も→
the terrible fate Rook and the children of the Phi Brain had to suffer,
オルペウス・オーダーが　クロンダイクに
利用される事もなかった！
and Klondike using the Orpheus Order would all never have happened!
パズルだ…　全部　パズルが悪いんだ！
（バロン）黙れ！
It's the puzzles!
The puzzles are to blame for all of it!
Silence!
パズルは悪くなんかねえ。
The puzzles aren't to blame here.
Puzzles aren't born with the intent of killing or hurting someone.
誰かを傷つけたくって
命を奪いたくって→
生まれてくるパズルなんか　ねえ！
みんな　作った人間が悪いんだ！
The people who make them are to blame!
お前も…　お前も　ギヴァーなら
聞こえるだろ!?　パズルの泣き声が！
If... If you're a Giver, then you must be able to hear
the puzzles' cries of pain!
（エニグマ）フッ…。　あきれたものだ。→
You're unbelievable.
さんざん傷つけられたというのに
まだ　パズルを信じるとは…→
You've suffered so much, yet you still believe in puzzles.
救いようのない　愚か者だ。
何だと!?
You're a fool beyond help.
What?
（エニグマ）だが…
それでこそ　招待のしがいがある。
However, that's exactly what makes you worth inviting.
招待？
Inviting?
待て！　ザガートカ！
Hold it, Zagadka!
Raetsel is waiting for you in Hell's Valley.
ヘルズバレーで　レイツェルが待っている！
ヘルズバレー!?
Hell's Valley?
She wants it to be the final puzzle battle.
（エニグマ）お前と
最後のパズルバトルをするためにな。
罠だよ　カイト！
It's a trap, Kaito!
ここまできて　罠など仕掛けんよ。
At this point, why would I bother with traps?
私にとっては
どうでもいい事だ→
I couldn't care less
君が勝とうが　レイツェルが勝とうが。
何!?
if you win or Raetsel does.
What?
（エニグマ）どちらが勝とうが
どちらかは死ぬ。→
Whoever wins, the other will suffer.
まあ　互いに潰し合い　共倒れに
なってくれるのが一番だが。→
I'd personally prefer it if you just killed each other there though.
Solve the puzzle, Daimon Kaito!
パズルを解くんだ！　大門カイト！
Daimon Kaito's coming here?
（レイツェル）大門カイトが　ここに？
[無線]（エニグマ）ああ。→
Yeah. The POG has located you. What will you do now, Raetsel?
ＰＯＧが　そちらの場所を
突き止めたようだ。→
どうする？　レイツェル。
I've had enough of running and hiding.
もう　逃げも隠れもしないわ。
I'm gonna defeat Daimon Kaito here!
ここで　大門カイトを倒す！
So reliable.
頼もしいじゃないか。
もう子猫じゃない　立派な山猫だ。
I can't call her a kitten anymore.
She's a proper wildcat.
さあ　いこう　ラヴーシュカ。
Let's go, Lovushka.
Let our dream, our puzzle, reach completion.
私たちの夢を…
２人のパズルを完成させるのだ。
I won't let anyone take Jin.
ジンは　誰にも渡さない。
Raetsel.
（ジン）レイツェル。→
戦え…。　お前の魂を
執念の全てを　パズルにぶつけろ。
Fight. Let the puzzle taste your soul, and how implacable you are.
Preview
I realized it myself.
Jin never hated puzzles or wanted to annihilate all puzzlers.